In Italy, there are four distinct and
powerful criminal empires. In Sicily,
you have the Kosanostra, who initially
created, shaped, and spread the
legendary image of the mafia and once
held the Italian state in a deadly
embrace. In Naples, you have the
sprawling chaotic camora, an
organization best described as a hydra
that poisons the earth for profit. In
Napoleia, the Sakra Corona unit reigns,
who are the gatekeepers to a shadow
economy flowing from the Balkans. And
finally, there is the one from the
mountains of Calabria, the impenetrable
and most powerful of them all in
Trangetta. These four criminal empires
don't just break the law. They have
enough financial firepower to distort
entire markets, infiltrate legitimate
businesses, and bring whole sectors of
the economy to their knees. The
Endangetta, for example, is estimated to
have annual revenues surpassing 53
billion. But to understand the Italian
mafia, you'll have to look at their
extremely clever geopolitical plays. And
each of these four Italian mobs do
geopolitics slightly differently. That
will all be revealed throughout this
video. So, let me break down these four
criminal empires one by one. Starting
with the one a lot of you probably know
thanks to Hollywood the Sicilian
Kosanostra which means our thing. Think
of them as the politicians. Their power
comes from a formal hierarchical
structure. Seemed the island of Sicily
is divided into territories controlled
by families all of which is overseen by
a board of directors called the
commission or Kula. Their geopolitical
signature has always been getting into
bed with power. For decades, they
maintained a deep alliance with Italy's
ruling political party, trading massive
blocks of votes for political protection
and a steady stream of lucrative
government contracts, especially in
construction. But while the Kosinostra
was playing the local political game,
another group was quietly building a
global empire. Meet the Enjangetta. If
Kosinostra are the politicians, the
Enjangetta are the CEOs. They are now
without a doubt the most powerful and
financially formidable criminal
organization on the planet. And their
secret is their structure. A structure
I'll reveal in just a moment. But first,
you may know that in some of my videos,
I've mentioned that I'm Danish. But a
little while ago, I wanted to be 100%
sure. So, I partnered with My Heritage
to do a DNA test, the sponsors of this
video. Right now, they're running a
special promotion where you can get your
own DNA kit for just $29, which is way
cheaper than any other company and the
best price ever. They simply sent me a
box in the mail with a kit where I had
to put a cotton swab in my mouth for
around a minute, put it in a vial, and
send it back to them. With this DNA,
they were able to break down my origins
across 42 different ethnicities and over
2,000 geographic regions. A few weeks
later, I got results in my email, and
here it is. As expected, I'm mostly
Danish, but surprisingly I have some DNA
from Sweden and the Netherlands. I did
know about the German DNA, but then some
small percentages from Eastern Europe,
England, and Norway are also kind of
surprising to me. There's also a DNA
match tool where you can find lost
relatives. Something important to
mention here is that My Heritage is
fully committed to your privacy. They
have it in their policy to never sell or
license your genetic data, which is
really reassuring when you're doing
something like this. So, if you're
curious about your own story, click the
link in the description or scan the QR
code that you see somewhere on screen
and use my code OBF to get your DNA kit
for just $29. Thanks again to My
Heritage for sponsoring this video.
Okay, now back to the Entraeta and why
their structure is so different and so
powerful. See, it's a decentralized
network of around 100 clans called
Entrina, which are almost exclusively on
blood family relationships. Their
strength is absolute trust. Since it's a
literal family business, it's nearly
impossible for police to infiltrate
them. This structure has allowed them to
become a global logistics conglomerate
whose main product is cocaine, and they
currently control 80% of the cocaine
supply in Europe. Then we have the
oldest and most chaotic of the groups,
the Neapolitan Kamora. Best described as
the street fighters. Unlike the other
two, the Kimora doesn't have any central
leadership. It's a horizontal fragmented
collection of hundreds of rival clans
that control neighborhoods and economic
sectors in and around Naples. This leads
to constant brutal turf wars. Although I
did find this article when I was editing
this video in my further research of
this topic assess that the mafia is
actually working together now and the
turf wars have kind of ended at least
for now. So yeah, I just wanted to add
that to the video. Their signature is
the parasitic exploitation of a dense
urban economy. They control everything
from smuggling at the port to the high
fashion counterfeit industry and most
infamously the region's waste
management. See, they get paid by
industries all over Europe to illegally
dump toxic waste, creating a devastating
environmental crisis in what's now
called the land of fires. In 1992, an
Exca boss confessed to investigators,
and I quote, "I don't deal with drugs
anymore. Now I have another business. It
pays more and the risk is less. It's
called garbage. For us, garbage is gold.
And he's right. In 2013 alone, the
illegal dumping of garbage and hazardous
waste brought in over€16 billion for
Italy's organized crime groups. And
finally, the new kid on the block, the
Sakla Corona unit or the United Sacred
Crown, the gatekeepers. Formed in a
prison in 1983. Their geopolitical
signature comes directly from the
geography of the region they're from.
Located on the hill of Italy, Apulia is
naturally the strategic bridge to the
east. They've leveraged this position to
become masters of the Adriatic Sea,
forming powerful alliances with Albanian
and other Balkan crime groups to smuggle
drugs, weapons, and people from Eastern
Europe into the rest of the EU. These
crime groups run short night runs across
the street of Otranto in fast boats and
regular-looking leisurecraft landing
near Otranto Printi and Santa Maria
delut beaches you have to pay the SCU to
use. If you don't they shut you down
immediately. In the '90s it was mostly
cigarettes that traveled through these
routes. But after the crackdowns the
same lanes shifted to Albanian weed,
Balcon route heroin, weapons and people.
So there you have it. Four families,
four unique business models. They're all
interesting and intricate, but one has
by far been the most successful, and
that is of course the Enjangeta. With
their corporate globalized approach,
they've built an international empire on
a scale the world has never seen before.
An empire that for the most part stands
on a single product. See, as we now
know, the engine of the modern mafia's
wealth and power is the international
narcotics trade. And the Enrangetta
built their global empire on the back of
cocaine. As I mentioned earlier, the
Entrancetas genius, however, was to do
what any smart legal corporation does
and cut out the middleman. They didn't
want to buy from a long chain of
suppliers. So, they sent their own
people to South America and established
direct business-to- business
relationships with the producing
cartels, quickly becoming trusted
partners, enabling them to negotiate
bulk prices at the source. But that's
just the beginning, because they also
managed the entire supply chain from
South America. They arrange for
transatlantic shipment often using West
African countries such as Guinea Buzzu,
Guinea and Sierra Leon, nations with
weak governance, poorest borders, and
high levels of corruption as massive
storage and transit hubs as well as
Caribbean islands like the Dominican
Republic, Trinidad and Jamaica, which
provide convenient mid-Atlantic staging
points to eventually end up at the final
destination, which is of course Europe
through the main container ports. But
one port stands out from the rest. This
is the port of Goya Taro, Enragetta's
crown jewel. As one of the biggest trans
shipment hubs in the Mediterranean, it's
the perfect nexus for their global
operations. And their method is
brilliant in its simplicity. It's called
the ripoff technique. Let me explain.
They don't need to own the ships or the
shipping companies. They just need to
own a few key people along the supply
chain. A corrupt worker in a South
American port will open a legitimate
sealed container bound for Europe, place
a shipment of cocaine inside, and reseal
it. The container number is then
communicated to a counterpart who simply
retrieves the drugs upon arrival. This
method is cheaper, harder to detect, and
spreads the risk across the vast
overwhelming flow of legitimate global
commerce. It's a system that turns the
lifeblood of our global economy into a
delivery service for the world's most
powerful criminal enterprise. Sure,
authorities do catch some of these
shipments, but their advantage is scale.
There's simply no way the authorities
will catch it all. Now, getting the
drugs in is only half the battle, as the
byproduct of this monopolistic control
of moving cocaine into Europe is cash.
Mountains and mountains of cash that
they need to launder somehow. This is
the final and most critical part of the
mafia's business model. Sophisticated
industrial scale money laundering. The
process always follows three stages.
Step one is placement. And this is also
the riskiest part. Getting the physical
cash into the financial system. They do
this by mixing it with the daily
receipts of a legitimate cash inensive
front business they own like a
restaurant, a bar, or a construction
company. The dirty money gets co-mingled
with clean money and deposited into a
bank account. The dirty clothes are now
in the machine. Step two is layering.
This is the wash cycle. The goal is to
obscure the money's origin through a
dizzying series of complex financial
transactions. The money is wired between
dozens of bank accounts and shell
companies in different countries,
converted into different currencies, and
used to buy and sell assets. The whole
point is to create a paper trail so
convoluted that no investigator could
ever hope to follow it back to its
source. The final step is integration.
The now clean money is reintroduced into
the legitimate economy. It can be used
to buy real estate, invest in the stock
market, or provide loans to other
businesses. This is how the mafia wages
economic warfare. See, during an
economic crisis, when a legitimate hotel
or construction firm is about to go
bankrupt and can't get a loan from a
bank, who has billions in cash ready to
buy it for pennies on the dollar? They
do. This is how they colonize entire
sectors of the legal economy.
Construction, waste management, tourism,
agriculture, they got it all. They
hollow out free market competition from
the inside, replacing it with a criminal
monopoly that makes them even richer and
more powerful. It's a slow motion
corporate takeover of Europe funded by
cocaine. But since there are four main
mafia in Italy, you might be wondering
why the Endrangetta ended up becoming
the most powerful, especially
considering the Sicilian mafia
Kosanostra is the oldest and was in fact
the most powerful in the 1980s. So what
happened? Well, in the 1980s, the
Italian state decided it was time to
fight back against the powerful Sicilian
Kosanostra, launching an all-out war
against them. What followed was the most
significant offensive ever launched
against organized crime. Enter the Maxi
trial. From 1986 to 1987, in this
specially constructed fortified bunker
courthouse in Palmo, the Italian state
put the entire leadership of the
Sicilian Kosinostra on trial at once.
475 mafiosi, meaning members of the
mafia, were indicted, resulting in 338
convictions and thousands of years in
prison sentences. The state had finally
broken the back of the Sicilian mafia.
But in doing so, it created a power
vacuum on the global stage, and a new
beast was waiting in the wings to take
its place. The very thing that made the
Kosinostra so powerful, its centralized
and hierarchical structure, was also its
fatal weakness. Once the informant
Tomasu Buskeeta gave the state the
organizational chart, they knew exactly
which heads to target. By decapitating
the leadership, they could the
entire organization. And it worked. But
the crackdown on the centralized
Kosinostra created the perfect opening
for the decentralized family-based
Entranceta to take over the global
market. Because they were a network, not
a pyramid. Their power was spread across
a 100 different blood family clans.
Cutting off one hat just meant another
family was ready to step up and take its
place. They were more resilient, more
adaptive, and more global than the
Sicilians had ever been. And this is why
the mafia endures. It's a constantly
evolving threat that adapts to the world
around it. The evolution from the rigid
kosinostra to the flexible envangetta
actually mirrors the evolution of modern
corporations from old school hierarchies
to agile 21st century networks. But
yeah, that is the Italian mafia. I hope
you like this video. If you did, please
leave a like down below and also
subscribe to the channel. And lastly,
thanks to My Heritage for sponsoring
this video. They are running a special
promotion right now where you can get
this DNA kit for just $29. So, click the
link in the description or scan the QR
code on screen and use my code OBF at
checkout to get this DNA kit for just
$29. But yeah, that's it for this video.
Thanks for watching and I'll see you in
the next